Guide to the Samuel Taylor Coleridge Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Samuel Taylor Coleridge collection
1797-1834
GEN MSS 880
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists of letters written by Samuel Taylor Coleridge to his friends and colleagues, including Joseph Cottle, James Gillman, and William Sotheby, along with a small selection of autograph manuscript poems and other writings.
Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection of documents was acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded at the folder level in the contents list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Samuel Taylor Coleridge (1772-1834)
British poet and author.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of letters written by Samuel Taylor Coleridge to his friends and colleagues, including Joseph Cottle, James Gillman, and William Sotheby, along with a small selection of autograph manuscript poems and other writings. The items in the collection were acquired by the library between 1921 and 1973.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1797-1834. II. Writings, circa 1825, undated.
Authors, English -- 19th century; English literature -- 19th century; English poetry -- 19th century; Authors, English; Poets -- England -- 19th century; Allsop, Thomas, 1795-1880; Blackwood, William, 1776-1834; Bowles, William Lisle, 1762-1850; Cottle, Joseph, 1770-1853; Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834; Cruckshank, Mary; Gillman, James, 1782-1839; Hatchett, Charles, 1765?-1847; Hutchinson, Sara, 1775-1835; Mudford, William, 1782-1848; Pettigrew, Thomas Joseph, 1791-1865; Purkis, Samuel; Sotheby, William, 1757-1833
- Correspondence, 1797-1834; Series I; 21
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by recipient.
  - Allsop, Thomas, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Purchased from Hamill and Barker on the Hubert Amer McGuire Memorial Fund, 1956.
    General note
    Autograph letter, signed; the enclosure, a letter of introduction to Sir Humphry Davy, is wanting
  - Blackwood, William, 1821 Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Autograph letter, signed.
    Purchased from Goodspeed on the Francis O. Matthiesen Fund, 1956.
  - Bowles, William Lisle, 1797 Oct 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift of Alfred L. Kellogg (Yale PhD 1941), 1949.
  - Clarkson, Mrs. Thomas, 1808 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1947.
    Autograph letter, signed; accompanied by a typed transcription.
  - Cottle, Joseph, 1813 Nov (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Gift of Julia Millhiser Gimbel, 1973.
  - Cottle, Joseph, 1814, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Two autograph letters, signed; accompanied by typed transcriptions.
  - Cruckshank, Mary, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Curtis, T., 1818 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Source unknown; formerly owned by Robinson Smith, Cheshire, Connecticut.
  - Dashwood, Mrs., 1834 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gillman, James, 1816 Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Purchased on the Hubert Amer McGuire Memorial Fund, 1949.
  - Gillman, Jame, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Library Associates Fund, 1950.
    Autograph letter, signed; accompanied by a typed transcript.
  - Hatchett, Charles, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1962.
  - Mudford, William, 1818? (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Purchased from Margel Gluck on the Edward Wells Southworth Fund, 1947.
  - Nixon, F., 1833 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Edmund Astley Prentis in memory of Russell G. Pruden (Yale 1906), 1949.
    Autograph note written in the third person; accompanied by a typed transcript.
  - Pettigrew, Thomas Joseph, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Bequest of Ray L. Murphy, 1954.
  - Purkis, Samuel, 1809 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reed, Mrs. Henry, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Gift of James Hosmer Penniman, 1921
    Envelope addressed to Mrs. Henry Reed, with Coleridge's name in the lower left corner, in his hand.
  - Sotheby, William, 1802 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Library Associates Fund, 1955.
    Autograph letter, signed; contains a draft of "Dejection: An Ode."
  - Unidentified recipient, 1812 Mar 3 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1960.
    Autograph letter, signed; concerning the subjects on which he might give a lecture.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1818 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Library Associates Fund, 1961.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1819 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Gift of Henry C. Hutchins, 1959.
    Copy in an unidentified hand of a letter by Coleridge on the subject of marriage.
- Writings, circa 1825, undated; Series II; 6
  Series II is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Christabel", undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Purchased from Seven Gables Bookshop on the Elizabeth W. Manwaring Fund and the Library Associates Fund, 1952.
    Manuscript copy in the hand of Sara Hutchinson, signed by Coleridge. Undated, but after 1801 and before October 1815, when it was sent to Lord Byron. It perhaps served as the printer's copy for the first edition, published by John Murray, London, 1816.
  - "The Dark Ladie, a Fragment", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Purchased from Quaritch with funds given in memory of Russell G. Pruden (Yale 1906), 1949.
    Autograph manuscript poem, signed; 15 stanzas of 4 lines each; paper watermarked 1833. First published in Coleridge's Poetical Works (London, 1834).
  - "Mementos III, IV, and V", undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Bequest of Russell G. Pruden, 1949.
    Autograph manuscript notes, with typed transcriptions; probably made in preparation for his "Aids to Reflection."
  - "The Spell: or Laugh til you Lose Him! A Melodrama", undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1961.
    Autograph manuscript outline of a projected dramatic romance, together with a list of the dramatis personae, with typed transcription.
  - "The Three Sorts of Friend", undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Source unknown.
    Autograph manuscript, signed, followed by a short autograph manuscript note to James Gilman
  - Notes on James Hillhouse's Hadad, circa 1825 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Purchased from Francis Edwards on the Plain Fund, 1943.
    Autograph manuscript notes written in the margins of a fragment (title page and introduction) of Hadad, a Dramatic Poem, by James Hillhouse (New York and London, 1825)